Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Geller, Bessie, 1974 April 12 and 22 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 83, 84a-b, Box 20, Reel 64a - 64d, Box 1, Folder 108)
    This interview was conducted on April 12 and April 22, 1974 by an unknown interviewer at an unknown location. The volume of the recording fluctuates, and there are large spaces of dead air between some sections. This interview covers Bessie Geller's childhood in Russia; her immigration to the United States (US) in 1912; and her participation in Socialism, Anarchism, and other radical political movements. Geller describes her father's reluctance to let her attend school in Russia, explaining that he believed that she would never find a husband if she was educated. She notes that the schools near her town were a privilege primarily for the children of the wealthy and not for Jewish children, but she recalls that her mother aided her in finding a tutor who instructed her in Russian, literature, and other subjects. She recounts wanting to immigrate to the US because she wanted to become independent from her parents; broaden the scope of her studies; and avoid an arranged marriage. She describes immigrating to the US with her sister and friend in 1912 and her mother convincing her father to sell his business and immigrate to the US with the rest of the family a year later.
    Geller recounts moving to Chicago, Illinois a few years after her family settled in New York, New York, in order to attend college and remain independent from her family. She focuses on her involvement in Socialism and Anarchism, recalling her approval of Socialist ideals of brotherhood and consideration; attending Socialist lectures, including one by Chaim Zhitlowsky; describing the relationships between different radical political ideologies; and comparing the radical political movements at the time of the interview with those of the past. She describes moving back to New York in 1927; raising her three daughters; and establishing a new group of friends among the members of radical political groups in New York City.
    Other topics include anecdotes about the life of her tutor; her love of the Yiddish language and Yiddish literature; her brief stay with her uncle and cousins in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; her children and grandchildren's educations, jobs, and marriages; her dislike of Communism; the hardships she endured when her children died; differences in how she and her mother handled their grief in regards to the loss of their children; the genealogy of her family; and her lifelong love of learning.
    Summary and subject cards are available for this interview.
    See also: Life Before Immigration or Migration; Politics; Leisure; and Ethnicity.
    New Yorkers at Work Oral History Collection, OH.001--Bessie Geller.
    Jews, Russian |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.; Women socialists |z New York (State) |z New York.; Women anarchists -- Political activity.
  - Gelo, Grace, 1974 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 160a-b, Box 101, Box 91, Reel 878a - 878b, Box 92, Reel 878c, Box 1, Folder 27)
    Grace Gelo was born in 1900 in Tunis, Tunisia. Her father was born in Sicily, Italy and immigrated to Tunisia after his military service in Italy. He worked as a shoemaker. Her mother was born in Sicily and immigrated as a small child with her family to Tunisia. The family immigrated to the United States (US) in 1914 and lived in the Greenwich Village neighborhood of Manhattan, New York.
    Gelo worked in the garment industry and was a member of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU). She married John Gelo, who was born in Italy and immigrated to the US in 1907. He was a member, organizer, and official of the ILGWU Local 89. He was a delegate of the American Labor Party and of the ILGWU. They lived in Brooklyn and had three daughters.
    This interview was conducted by Janice Albert in 1974 at an unspecified location. The interview covers Grace Gelo's childhood in Tunis, Tunisia; her immigration to the United States (US); her working life; her husband's union and political activity; and their children. Gelo discusses her childhood in Tunis, including her education and her parents' backgrounds. She provides a short history of the colonization of Tunisia and of the ethnic groups in Tunis. She discusses her family's immigration to the US and the ethnic groups in the Greenwich Village neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She discusses her strict upbringing and rules her father imposed upon her; her courtship with her husband under these rules; and her younger sister's rebellion against the rules. She discusses having to leave school in order to work to support her family and working as a finisher on men's clothes. She describes the first factory in which she worked; the ethnic demographics of the workers, mainly Italian and Jewish, and the language barrier between the two groups; and her unhappiness in her work and her difficulty communicating with the Jewish workers. She describes working conditions in the factories; her dissatisfaction with them; and her opinion that the workers were seriously mistreated.
    Gelo discusses her husband's union and political activity; his participation in early organizing efforts of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), particularly in 1909, and his election as a delegate of the American Labor Party (ALP). She discusses attending conventions with her husband, including American Federation of Labor national conventions, ILGWU national conventions, and political conventions as a delegate of the ALP. Other topics include her father's insistence that his children retain their Italian identity in both Tunisia and US; her participation in social activities at the time of the interview; and her daughters.
    See also: Life Before Immigration or Migration; and Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York, New York and the United States.
    Summary and index cards are available for this interview. An electronic transcript of this interview is also available by request.
    Italians |z Tunisia |x History |y 20th century.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 89 (New York, N.Y.)
  - Glick, Hyman, 1974 October 21 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 58, Box 92, Reel 883a - 883b, Box 1, Folder 29)
    Hyman Glick was born Hyman Gleot in Vilna, Russia in 1883. He had five brothers and two sisters. His father was a teacher at a cheder, or Jewish elementary school. Glick attended university and married in Dvinsk, Russia. He immigrated to the United States (US) in 1902 and changed his name to Glick. He lived in the US for three years before his wife immigrated with their son.
    This interview was conducted by Suzanne Michel at Hyman Glick's home in Brooklyn, New York on October 21, 1974. One of Glick's grandsons assists in the interview but is not identified by name. The interview covers Glick's childhood in Vilna, Russia; his immigration to the United States (US); his working life; and his family. Glick discusses his education at a cheder in Vilna until the age of 18 and at a university in Dvinsk, Russia where he studied chemistry and trained as a dyer. He discusses his wife and mother-in-law deciding for him to immigrate to the US in order to avoid being drafted into the Russian Army; living with his wife's relatives in the US; and his wife's uncle deciding he should change his name from Gleot to Glick because it was easier to spell. He recounts finding and losing jobs in different industries before settling in the dry cleaning industry; the salary he received; and the number of days he worked per week at these jobs. He discusses borrowing money in order to bring his wife and son over to the US and living in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. He recounts his business ventures, including buying two dry cleaning stores in Manhattan and buying and selling dry cleaning stores in order to make a profit. Other topics include attending movies and the Yiddish theater on Sundays and collecting clothes from customers with a horse and wagon in the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    Dry cleaning industry |x Employees |z New York (State)
  - Godet, Rose, 1973 April 24 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 210, Box 20, Reel 67a, Box 21, Reel 67b)
    Rose Godet was born in the Dominican Republic in 1896. She was of French descent. She immigrated to the United States with her father in 1919. She worked in Manhattan, New York for the Charles Broadway Rouss department store as a saleswoman, as a translator for a mail order company, and as a packager for the National Biscuit Company.
    This interview was conducted on April 24, 1973 by Victor Scheluchin at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens, on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York. The main topics discussed include Rose Godet's childhood in the Dominican Republic, her feelings about immigrating to the United States (US), her work experience, and her personal experiences in New York, New York. Godet begins by discussing her early life in the Dominican Republic, including being of French descent; speaking multiple languages; and her father working for the Puccini Shipping Company. Her early experiences in New York City include living on 140th Street in Manhattan; deciding to only live in Manhattan; disliking living in the US initially because she had never worked before; feeling lonely in the city; and finding the US to be substantially more expensive than the Dominican Republic. Godet discusses her confusion regarding segregation, having never witnessed white flight before coming to the US. She discusses her personal experiences during the Prohibition era and the Great Depression, including an Irish friend giving her bootleg liquor, though she did not like the taste; enjoying visiting speakeasies; and being employed pressing silk underwear. She talks about World War II and her fear of air raid drills; that minimum wage requirements implemented by Franklin Roosevelt were not enforced; and her belief that the US government would pull men off the streets and force them into the military. She notes her work experience, which included working as a saleswoman and interpreter for the Charles Broadway Rouss department store on Broadway in Manhattan and learning to type in order to work for a mail order company translating orders received in Spanish or French. She discusses her employment at the National Biscuit Company packing cookies after she began to lose her eyesight, and feeling exploited by the company due to the minimal vacation time, long hours, and low wages.
    Segregation |z New York (State) |z New York.; Prohibition |z New York (State) |z New York
  - Goldman, Minna, 1974 April 18 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 82, Box 83, Reel 810a, Box 84, Reel 810b, Box 1, Folder 30)
    Minna Goldman was born in Bucharest, Romania in the late 19th century and was the eldest of seven children. She immigrated to the United States (US) and returned to Romania twice before settling permanently in the US. Her first immigration to the US was in 1907 with her father and younger brother, who died in the Netherlands during their travels. Goldman and her father settled in New York, New York, where her father worked as an umbrella maker and she worked in a blouse factory. They returned to Romania after six months in the US. Goldman returned to the US in 1910 with a cousin and worked refurbishing old umbrellas. She saved enough money to buy passage for her parents and five siblings though they declined to travel. She returned to Romania in 1912 and resumed her education. After leaving school, she worked in a foreign language bookstore and for the American Red Cross in Bucharest. She returned to the US in 1920. She worked in a bank before meeting her husband, who was a pharmacist and owned a pharmacy. She worked in the pharmacy until the birth of their daughter. After the death of her husband, she worked for the Jewish Labor Committee in Manhattan.
    This interview was conducted on April 18, 1974. The interviewer and location are unknown. The interview covers Minna Goldman's multiple immigrations to the United States (US) and returns to Romania, her working life in both countries, and her extended family. Goldman discusses her multiple immigrations to the US between 1907 and 1920 and her reasons for returning to Romania before permanently settling in the US in 1920. She discusses the pogrom that led to her initial immigration with her father and one of her brothers in 1907; the death of her brother during their travels; and her father's decision to return to Romania after six months in US. She discusses her father's work as an umbrella maker and his decision to send her to work rather than school, in order to save money for their return to Romania. She describes her unhappiness at having to leave the US as she felt it had a more egalitarian society than Romania. She recalls her decision to return to the US in 1910 and forego her education in order to work and save money to send to her family in Romania. She describes her work refurbishing old umbrellas and recalls her decision to return to Romania when her family decided not to immigrate to the US.
    Goldman discusses resuming her education in Romania and learning French and English with a private tutor. She describes her work in a foreign language bookstore in Bucharest and how it led to her improving her knowledge of French and English. She discusses her work with the American Red Cross in Bucharest; the details of her job; and the types of people who came to them for assistance. She discusses her life during World War I, including the occupation of Romania by German soldiers; her opinion that Jews received fair treatment from the occupiers; the pogrom that devastated Bucharest's Jewish community after Armistice Day in 1919; and how that led to her decision to immigrate to the US for a third and final time.
    In discussing her life in the US after her immigration in 1920, Goldman recounts her work at a bank before her marriage; her introduction to her husband; and her work with him in his pharmacy. She discusses the immigration patterns, careers, and marital histories of her siblings and her daughter's accomplishments.
    Pogroms |z Romania |x History |y 20th century.; World War, 1914-1918 |z Romania.
  - Goldman, Sam and Dora Shapiro, 1973 December (Box 84, Reel 814c - 814e, Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 51a-b, Box 1, Folder 31)
    Sam Goldman and Dora Shapiro were siblings born in Gorlice in Polish Galicia. They had one brother and two sisters. Their father managed an oil refinery where the family lived until it closed. Their mother managed a candy store owned by the family. Goldman immigrated to the United States in 1913, and Shapiro and the rest of the family immigrated in 1921.
    Goldman worked in the fur industry and owned his own factory in New York, New York. He married in 1922. He was a member of the Freemasons.
    Shapiro worked in the garment industry and was a member of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. She met her first husband during a vacation to Cuba and they married in 1929. They divorced a few years later and she married a second time.
    This interview was conducted by David Lamb at Sam Goldman's house in Brooklyn, New York in December 1973. Dora Shapiro, Goldman's sister, participates in the interview. The interview covers Goldman and Shapiro's childhood in Gorlice, Poland; their immigration experiences; and their working lives. They discuss their early lives in Gorlice, including the differences in their educations and the living arrangements of their family. They discuss the differences between religious and secular schools, including the curricula; the fact that only the most religious boys attended the religious schools; and games they would play during recess. Goldman and Shapiro describe Gorlice; the fact that Jews lived among other religious groups in the town; the relationship between the two groups, including anti-Semitism; the social hierarchy amongst the Jewish residents; and the layout and architecture of the town. They discuss their religious upbringing, in particular the separation between men and women and the fact that women were not required to attend religious services.
    Goldman and Shapiro discuss their immigrations to the United States (US), including their reasons for immigrating; the processes by which they arranged their passages; the pattern in which their family members immigrated; and their voyages across the Atlantic Ocean. Goldman discusses the eight years during which he lived in the US without his family; the obligation he felt to provide support for his family in Poland; and his work in the fur industry, including owning his own business. Shapiro recounts the family's first impressions of New York, New York, including how bustling it seemed compared to their town in Poland and how crowded the city was. She discusses the education and work experiences of their siblings in the US.
    Shapiro discusses her work in the garment industry in New York City, including the conditions in the factories in which she worked; the type of work she did, including folding, cutting, and draping dresses; and her feelings about the different types of work. She discusses her membership in the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), including strikes in which she participated.
    Other topics include Goldman and Shapiro's opinions on socialism, Zionism, Judaism, and politics in the US; differences in citizenship requirements between the times each applied; how they met their spouses; and social activities in which they participated.
    See also: Politics.
    Gorlice (Poland) |x History.
  - Goldstein, Anna, 1973 March 24 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 15, Box 92, Reel 885a - 885b, Box 93, Reel 885c, Box 1, Folder 32)
    Anna Goldstein was born in Romania. She immigrated to the United States in 1907. She worked in a garment factory on Orchard Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She married in 1909 and had at least two children. She owned a health food store in the 1930s.
    This interview was conducted by Wendy Fisher on March 24, 1973 at Anna Goldstein's home in the Long Island City neighborhood of Queens, New York. Goldstein was Fisher's grandmother. The interview covers Goldstein's immigration to the United States (US), her life in the US, and her family. Goldstein's train of thought can be hard to follow throughout the interview.
    Goldstein discusses immigrating to the US in order to find work; arranging to have an acquaintance pay her passage to the US; and losing all of her possessions, including the addresses of her cousin and friend in New York, before arriving in the US. She recalls spending every night for two weeks looking for her cousin's store on Eldridge Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. She describes her early experiences in New York City, including her living arrangements; her work in a garment factory; and the way in which she met her husband. She recounts returning to Romania after the birth of her first son in 1911; seeking a cure for his spastic diplegia in Bucharest; being trapped in Romania after the outbreak of the First Balkan War in 1912; and returning to the US in 1913. She discusses her husband's dress factory on Columbia Street in the Lower East Side and his bankruptcy while she was in Europe.
    Balkan Peninsula |x History |y War of 1912-1913 |v Personal narratives.
  - Goren, Pauline, 1973 December (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 50b, Box 93, Reel 887a, Box 1, Folder 33)
    Pauline Winnik Goren was born in Pinsk, Russia around 1904. She was one of six children. Her father was a potato farmer and she managed his laborers. Her mother managed the household. One of her brothers worked as a furrier and the other was a lumber merchant.
    Goren immigrated to the United States in 1921. Two of her brothers had immigrated 15 years before her and her parents immigrated six months after she did. She worked for a brief period in the fur industry. She married Sol Goren and had two daughters.
    This interview was conducted by David Lamb in Pauline Goren's home in Brooklyn, New York in December 1973. Topics include Goren's childhood in Russia, her immigration to the United States (US), and her life in the US. Goren discusses her childhood in Pinsk, Russia, including her family; her neighborhood; the hierarchy amongst Jews in the area; her education in religious and public schools; and the differences in education for boys and girls. She discusses religion, including her family being extremely religious and the difference in religious observance between men and women. She discusses her family's decision to immigrate to the US due to rising anti-Semitism and pogroms in Pinsk, and the outbreak of World War I. She recounts hiding during pogroms, sometimes with the aid of Catholic priests in her neighborhood. She describes her father's potato farm, including the ownership of the land and her father's lease on it; her management of the laborers, who were not Jewish; and the relationship between herself and the laborers. She describes the industries in Pinsk and the types of people employed in the factories. She discusses reactions to the Russian Revolution in Pinsk and her family's decision to immigrate soon after the Revolution. She discusses her family's chain of immigration and two of her brothers who lived in the US assisting her immigration.
    Goren discusses her life in New York, New York, including attending school and working in the fur industry. She describes her work in the fur industry, initially in a factory finishing fur coats and then working in a fur showroom. She explains that she left the workforce when she married Sol Goren. Other topics include her social life before and after her marriage; her two daughter and their families; and the differences in education and religious observance in the US and Russia.
    See also: Goren, Sol.
    Pogroms |z Russia |x History |y 20th century.; Antisemitism |z Russia |x History |y 20th century.
  - Goren, Sol, 1973 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 48a-b, 49, Box 84, Reel 816a, Box 85, Reel 816b - 816c, Box 1, Folder 34)
    Sol Goren was born in 1903 in David-Gorodok, Russia. He was one of eight children. His parents owned a hotel, in which the family lived. His father was an employment agent for the local lumber industry and his mother managed the family's hotel. He and his family immigrated to the United States in 1922. He worked as an operator and a cutter in the fur industry and owned his own fur shop. He was a member of the International Fur and Leather Workers Union of the United States and Canada. He married Pauline Winnik Goren, with whom he had two daughters.